It's a conflict that rarely hits the headlines.
التي نادرًا ما تتصدر عناوين الصحف.
It happens right here, in the Democratic Republic of Congo.
هذا الصراع يجري هنا في جمهوية كونغو الديمقراطية.
Now, most people outside of Africa don't know much about the war in Congo,
والآن، معظم من يعيش خارج أفريقيا لا يعلم كثيرًا عن الحرب في الكونغو
so let me give you a couple of key facts.
فاسمحوا لي أن أقدم لكم بعض الحقائق الرئيسية عنها.
The Congolese conflict is the deadliest conflict since World War II.
الصراع الكونغولي هو الأكثر دموية منذ الحرب العالمية الثانية.
It has caused almost four million deaths.
حيث تسبب في مقتل أربع ملايين شخص تقريبًا
It has destabilized most of Central Africa for the past 18 years.
وزعزع معظم أجزاء أفريقيا الوسطى في السنوات الثمانية عشر الماضية.
It is the largest ongoing humanitarian crisis in the world.
وهو أكبر أزمة إنسانية مستمرة في العالم.
That's why I first went to Congo in 2001.
وكان هذا سبب ذهابي إلى الكونغو عام 2001.
I was a young humanitarian aid worker, and I met this woman who was my age.
كنت عاملة إغاثة إنسانية شابة، والتقيت بهذه المرأة التي كانت في نفس عمري
She was called Isabelle.
كان اسمها إيزابيل.
Local militias had attacked Isabelle's village.
كانت الميليشيات المحلية قد هاجمت قرية إيزابيل
They had killed many men, raped many women.
وقتلت العديد من الرجال واغتصبت الكثير من النساء
They had looted everything.
ونهبت كل شيء
And then they wanted to take Isabelle,
ثم أرادت تلك الميليشيات أخذ إيزابيل،
but her husband stepped in,
لكن زوجها تدخل،
and he said, "No, please don't take Isabelle.
ثم قال:"لا، أرجوكم لا تأخذوا إيزابيل.
Take me instead."
خذوني بدلاً عنها."
So he had gone to the forest with the militias,
فذهب إلى الغابة مع الميليشيات،
and Isabelle had never seen him again.
ولم ترَه إيزابيل مرة أخرى.
Well, it's because of people like Isabelle and her husband
من أجل من هم مثل إيزابيل وزوجها
that I have devoted my career to studying this war
كرست حياتي المهنية لدراسة هذا العالم
that we know so little about.
الذي لا نعرف سوى القليل عنه.
Although there is one story about Congo that you may have heard.
بالرغم من وجود قصة واحدة عن الكنغو قد تكونوا سمعتم عنها،
It's a story about minerals and rape.
وهي قصة تتعلق بعمال المناجم والاغتصاب.
Policy statements and media reports
البيانات السياسية والتقارير الإعلامية
both usually focus on a primary cause of violence in Congo --
تركز عادةً على واحد من المسببات الرئيسية للعنف في الكونغو،
the illegal exploitation and trafficking of natural resources --
وهو الاستغلال غير القانوني والاتجار غير المشروع بالموارد الطبيعية،
and on a main consequence --
وعلى الأثر المترتب الرئيسي
sexual abuse of women and girls as a weapon of war.
العنف الجنسي للنساء والفتيات كسلاح للحرب.
So, not that these two issues aren't important and tragic. They are.
لا أنكر أن هاتين القضيتين مهمّتين
But today I want to tell you a different story.
ولكني اليوم أرغب في الحديث عن قصة مختلفة.
I want to tell you a story that emphasizes a core cause
أريد أن أحكي لكم قصة تركز على المسبب الرئيسي
of the ongoing conflict.
للصراع القائم.
Violence in Congo is in large part driven by local bottom-up conflicts
الصراع في الكونغو تقوده الصراعات المحلية التصاعدية
that international peace efforts have failed to help address.
التي أخفقت جهود السلام الدولية في معالجتها
The story starts from the fact that not only is Congo notable
القصة تبدأ من حقيقة أن الكونغو ليست معروفة
for being the world's worst ongoing humanitarian crisis,
بكونها تمثل أسوأ أزمة إنسانية مستمرة في العالم فحسب،
but it is also home to some of the largest
ولكنها أيضًا موطن لبعض أكبر
international peacebuilding efforts in the world.
مساعي بناء السلام الدولية في العالم.
Congo hosts the largest
تستضيف الكونغو مهمّة
and most expensive United Nations peacekeeping mission in the world.
الأمم المتحدة لحفظ السلام الأكبر والأكثر كلفة في العالم
It was also the site of the first European-led peacekeeping mission,
كما كانت المقر لأول مهمة تقودها أوروبا لحفظ السلام،
and for its first cases ever,
وبالنسبة لأول قضاياها،
the International Criminal Court chose to prosecute Congolese warlords.
اختارت المحكمة الجنائية الدولية محاكمة بعض القادة العسكريين الكونغوليين
In 2006, when Congo held the first free national elections in its history,
في عام 2006،عندما عقدت الكونغو أول انتخابات حرة في تاريخها،
many observers thought that an end to violence in the region had finally come.
اعتقد العديد من المراقبين أن ذلك يُمثل نهاية العنف في المنطقة أخيرًا.
The international community lauded the successful organization of these elections
وقد أشاد المجتمع الدولي بالتنظيم الناجح لتلك الانتخابات
as finally an example of successful international intervention
باعتبارها مثالاً لتدخلٍ دوليِ ناجح
in a failed state.
في دولةٍ عاجزة.
But the eastern provinces
غير أن الأقاليم الشرقية
have continued to face massive population displacements
واصلت معاناتها مع النزوح الجماعي للسكان
and horrific human rights violations.
والانتهاكات الفظيعة لحقوق الانسان.
Shortly before I went back there last summer,
قبل أن أعود إلى هناك الصيف الماضي بوقت قصير،
there was a horrible massacre in the province of South Kivu.
وقعت مذبحة فظيعة في مقاطعة كيفو الجنوبية.
Thirty-three people were killed.
حيث قُتل فيها 33 شخص
They were mostly women and children,
معظمهم كانوا من النساء والأطفال،
and many of them were hacked to death.
والعديد منهم قُطِّعت أجسادهم حتى الموت.
During the past eight years,
خلال السنوات الثمان الماضية،
fighting in the eastern provinces has regularly reignited
أشعل القتال في الأقاليم الشرقية
full-scale civil and international war.
حرب محلية ودولية شاملة.
So basically, every time we feel that we are on the brink of peace,
ففي كل مرة نشعر أننا على شفا تحقيق السلام،
the conflict explodes again.
يشتعل الصراع مجدّدًا.
Why?
لماذا؟
Why have the massive international efforts
لماذا أخفقت المجهود الدولية الشاملة
failed to help Congo achieve lasting peace and security?
في مساعدة الكونغو على تحقيق السلام والأمن الدائمَين؟
Well, my answer to this question revolves around two central observations.
جوابي على هذا السؤال يدور حول ملاحظتين رئيسيتين.
First, one of the main reasons for the continuation of violence in Congo
الأولى، أحد الأسباب الرئيسية لاستمرار العنف في الكونغو
is fundamentally local --
هو سبب محلّي بصورة أساسية.
and when I say local,
وعندما أقول محلي
I really mean at the level of the individual, the family,
فالمقصود على مستوى الفرد والأسرة،
the clan, the municipality, the community, the district,
والعشيرة، والمجلس البلدي، والمجتمع، والحي،
sometimes the ethnic group.
وأحيانًا المجموعة العِرقية.
For instance, you remember the story of Isabelle that I told you.
على سبيل المثال، لا بد أنكم تذكرون قصة إيزابيل التي أخبرتكم عنها.
Well, the reason why militias had attacked Isabelle's village
السبب الذي دفع الميليشيات إلى مهاجمة قرية إيزابيل
was because they wanted to take the land
كان رغبتهم في الاستيلاء على الأرض
that the villagers needed to cultivate food and to survive.
التي كان أهالي القريبة يحتاجونها لزراعة الغذاء الذي يؤمن عيشهم.
The second central observation is that international peace efforts
الملاحظة الرئيسية الثانية تتمثل في أن جهود السلام الدولية
have failed to help address local conflicts
أخفقت في معالجة الصراعات المحلية
because of the presence of a dominant peacebuilding culture.
بسبب وجود ثقافة بناء سلام سائدة.
So what I mean is that
وما أعنيه هو أن
Western and African diplomats,
الدبلوماسيين الغربيين والأفارقة
United Nations peacekeepers, donors,
وقوات حفظ السلام التابعة للأمم المتحدة، والجهات المانحة،
the staff of most nongovernmental organizations
وموظفي معظم المنظمات غير الحكومية
that work with the resolution of conflict,
التي تعمل على حل النزاع،
they all share a specific way of seeing the world.
جميعهم يتشاركون نفس الطريقة التي ينظرون إلى العالم بها.
And I was one of these people, and I shared this culture,
وكنت واحدة من هؤلاء، وقد شاركتهم هذه الثقافة،
so I know all too well how powerful it is.
لذا أنا أعرف جيّدا مدى قوتها.
Throughout the world, and throughout conflict zones,
في جميع أنحاء العالم وفي جميع أنحاء مناطق النزاع،
this common culture shapes the intervener's understanding
تُشكل هذه الثقافة الشائعة فِهم المتدخلين
of the causes of violence
حول أسباب العنف
as something that is primarily located in the national and international spheres.
باعتباره موجود بشكل أساسي على الصعيدين القومي والدولي.
It shapes our understanding of the path toward peace
إنها تشكل فهمنا للطريق نحو السلام
as something again that requires top-down intervention
الذي يتسلزم مرة أخرى تدخلاً تنازليًّا
to address national and international tensions.
لمواجهة التوتر القومي والدولي.
And it shapes our understanding of the roles of foreign actors
كما تشكل فهمنا لأدوار الممثلين الأجانب
as engaging in national and international peace processes.
المشاركين في عمليات السلام القومية والدولية.
Even more importantly, this common culture
والأهم من ذلك أن هذه الثقافة الشائعة
enables international peacebuilders to ignore the micro-level tensions
تمكِّن بُناة السلام الدوليين من تجاهل التوترات الجزئية
that often jeopardize the macro-level settlements.
التي غالبًا ما تشكل خطرًا على الاستقرارات ذات المستوى الكلي.
So for instance, in Congo,
فمثلاً، في الكونغو
because of how they are socialized and trained,
بسبب طريقة تدريبهم ودمجهم في المجتمع،
United Nations officials, donors, diplomats,
يقوم موظفو الأمم المتحدة، والمتبرعون، والدبلوماسيون
the staff of most nongovernmental organizations,
وطواقم معظم المنظمات غير الحكومية،
they interpret continued fighting and massacres as a top-down problem.
بتفسير المعارك والمذابح المتواصلة على أنها مشكلة ذات توجه تنازلي.
To them, the violence they see
فبالنسبة لهم، العنف الذي يشهدونه
is the consequence of tensions between President Kabila
هو نتيجة التوترات بين الرئيس كابيلا
and various national opponents,
وعدد من المعارضين المحليين،
and tensions between Congo, Rwanda and Uganda.
والتوترات بين الكونغو ورواندا وأوغندا.
In addition, these international peacebuilders view local conflicts
إضافة إلى أن بناة السلام أولئك ينظرون للصراعات المحلية
as simply the result of national and international tensions,
على أنها ببساطة نتيجة للتوترات القومية والدولية
insufficient state authority,
والسلطة الحكومية غير الكافية
and what they call the Congolese people's so-called inherent penchant for violence.
وما يطلقون عليه ميل الشعب الكونغولي الموروث للعنف.
The dominant culture also constructs intervention
كما أن الثقافة السائدة تبني التدخل
at the national and international levels
على المستويين القومي والدولي
as the only natural and legitimate task for United Nations staffers and diplomats.
كونه المهمة الوحيدة الطبيعية المشروعة لموظفي الأمم المتحدة ودبلوماسيها.
And it elevates the organization of general elections,
وتصعّد تنظيم الانتخابات العامة،
which is now a sort of cure-all,
التي تُعد الآن علاجًا لجميع العلل،
as the most crucial state reconstruction mechanism
إلى حد اعتبارها الآلية الأكثر حسمًا لإعادة بناء الدولة
over more effective state-building approaches.
أو المقاربة الأكثر فعالية لبناء الدولة.
And that happens not only in Congo but also in many other conflict zones.
وهذا لا يحدث في الكونغو فقط بل أيضًا في مناطق صراع عديدة
But let's dig deeper,
لكن لنتعمق في المسألة،
into the other main sources of violence.
أي في مصادر العنف الرئيسية.
In Congo, continuing violence
في الكونغو، العنف المتواصل
is motivated not only by the national and international causes
لا يعود للمسببات القومية والدولية فحسب،
but also by longstanding bottom-up agendas
ولكنه ناتج أيضًا عن الأجندات التنازلية المتواجدة منذ زمن
whose main instigators are villagers, traditional chiefs,
التي يدبرها أساسًا القرويين والزعماء التقليديين
community chiefs or ethnic leaders.
أو زعماء المجتمع أو القادة العرقيين.
Many conflicts revolve around political, social and economic stakes
تدور العديد من الصراعات حول ركائز سياسية واجتماعية واقتصادية
that are distinctively local.
االتي يظهر بجلاء أنها محلية.
For instance, there is a lot of competition
على سبيل المثال، يوجد قدر كبير من المنافسة
at the village or district level
على مستوى القرى أو المقاطعات
over who can be chief of village or chief of territory
على تولي زعامة القرية أو المقاطعة
according to traditional law,
وفقًا للقانون التقليدي،
and who can control the distribution of land
وعلى تولي مسؤلية توزيع الأراضي
and the exploitation of local mining sites.
واستغلال مواقع التنقيب المحلية.
This competition often results in localized fighting,
وعادة ما ينشأ عن هذه المنافسة صراع محلي،
for instance in one village or territory,
فمثلاً في إحدى القرى أو المقاطعات،
and quite frequently, it escalates into generalized fighting,
وعلى نحو مستمر، يُصعد الصراع إلى القتال المعمم
so across a whole province,
ليشمل كامل المنطقة
and even at times into neighboring countries.
وحتى في بعض الأحيان الدول المجاورة.
Take the conflict between Congolese of Rwandan descent
لنأخذ على سبيل المثال الصراع بين الكونغوليين المنحدرين من روندا
and the so-called indigenous communities of the Kivus.
وما يدعون بمحتمعات الشعوب الأصلية في كيفوس.
This conflict started in the 1930s during Belgian colonization,
بدأ الصراع في ثلاثينات القرن الماضي أثناء الاستعمار البلجيكي
when both communities competed over access to land and to local power.
عندما تنافس المجتمعان على الوصول للأراضي والسلطة المحلية
Then, in 1960, after Congolese independence,
ثم، في عام 1960، بعد الاستقلال الكونغولي،
it escalated because each camp tried to align with national politicians,
تصاعد الصراع لأن كل معسكر سعى إلى التوافق مع السياسيين الوطنيين
but still to advance their local agendas.
مع سعيهم أيضًا إلى التقدم بأجندتهم المحلية.
And then, at the time of the 1994 genocide in Rwanda,
ومن ثم، في وقت الإبادة الجماعية في رواندا عام 1994،
these local actors allied with Congolese and Rwandan armed groups,
تحالف أولئك الممثلون المحليين مع الجماعات المسلحة الكونغولية والرواندية،
but still to advance their local agendas in the provinces of the Kivus.
ولكنهم مع ذلك تقدموا بأجندتهم المحلية في مقاطعة كيفوس.
And since then, these local disputes over land and local power
ومنذ ذلك الحين، هذه النزاعات المحلية على الأراضي والسلطة
have fueled violence,
غذّت العنف،
and they have regularly jeopardized
ودائمًا ما كانت تشكل خطرًا
the national and international settlements.
على االمستوطنات الوطنية والدولية.
So we can wonder why in these circumstances
لذا يمكننا أن نتسائل لماذا في مثل تلك الظروف
the international peacebuilders have failed to help implement
فشل بناة السلام الدوليين في تنفيذ
local peacebuilding programs.
برامج بناء السلام المحلية.
And the answer is that international interveners
والجواب أن المتدخلين الدوليين
deem the resolution of grassroots conflict
يعتبرون حل النزاع الأساسي
an unimportant, unfamiliar, and illegitimate task.
هو مهمة غير مهمة وغير مألوفة وغير شرعية.
The very idea of becoming involved at the local level clashes fundamentally
فكرة الانخراط على المستوى المحلي تتصادم بشكل أساسي
with existing cultural norms,
مع المعايير الثقافية الحالية،
and it threatens key organizational interests.
وهي تهدد المصالح التنظيمية الرئيسية.
For instance, the very identity of the United Nations
على سبيل المثال، هوية الأمم المتحدة
as this macro-level diplomatic organization
بصفتها منظمة دبلوماسية ذات مستوى جزئي
would be upended if it were to refocus on local conflicts.
ستتغير تغيرًا حادًّا لو أنها ستعيد التركيز على النزاعات المحلية.
And the result is that neither the internal resistance
والنتيجة أنه لا المقاومة الداخلية
to the dominant ways of working
لوسائل العمل المهيمنة
nor the external shocks
ولا الاصطدامات الخارجية
have managed to convince international actors that they should reevaluate
تمكنت من إقناع الممثلين الدوليين بضرورة إعادة تقييم
their understanding of violence and intervention.
فهمهم للعنف والتدخل.
And so far, there have been only very few exceptions.
وحتى الآن لا توجد إلا استثناءات قليلة جدًًا.
There have been exceptions, but only very few exceptions,
كان هناك استتثناءات ولكنها قليلة جدًّا
to this broad pattern.
مقارنة بهذا النمط العريض.
So to wrap up, the story I just told you
وتلخيصًا لحديثي، القصة التي رويتها لكم للتو
is a story about how a dominant peacebuilding culture
تظهر كيف أن ثقافة بناء السلام السائدة
shapes the intervener's understanding of what the causes of violence are,
تشكل فهم المتدخل لأسباب العنف
how peace is made,
وكيف يُصنع السلام،
and what interventions should accomplish.
وما التدخلات الواجب تنفيذها.
These understandings enable international peacebuilders
تمكن تلك المفاهيم بناة السلام الدوليين
to ignore the micro-level foundations
من تجاهل الأسس ذات المستوى الجزئي
that are so necessary for sustainable peace.
التي تشكل أهمية كبيرة للسلام المستدام.
The resulting inattention to local conflicts
عدم الاكتراث الناتج للنزاعات المحلية
leads to inadequate peacebuilding in the short term
يقود إلى جهود غير كافية لبناء السلام على المدى القصير
and potential war resumption in the long term.
واستمرار محتمل للحرب على المدى الطويل.
And what's fascinating is that this analysis
والمبهر أن هذا التحليل
helps us to better understand many cases of lasting conflict
يساعدنا على تحسين فهمنا للعديد من قضايا النزاع الدائم
and international intervention failures, in Africa and elsewhere.
وإخفاقات التدخل الدولي في أفريقيا وأي مكان آخر.
Local conflicts fuel violence in most war and post-war environments,
النزاعات المحلية تغذي العنف في معظم بيئات الحرب وما بعدها،
from Afghanistan to Sudan to Timor-Leste,
من أفغانستان إلى السودان إلى تيمور الشرقية،
and in the rare cases where there have been comprehensive,
وفي الحالات النادرة، حيث وُجدت مبادرات
bottom-up peacebuilding initiatives,
بناء السلام التصاعدية الشاملة،
these attempts have been successful at making peace sustainable.
نجحت تلك المساعي في استدامة السلام.
One of the best examples is the contrast
أحد أفضل الأمثلة هو الفارق بين
between the relatively peaceful situation in Somaliland,
الوضع السلمي نسبيًّا في أرض الصومال،
which benefited from sustained grassroots peacebuilding initiatives,
التي استفادت من مبادرات بناء السلام الأساسية المستمرة،
and the violence prevalent in the rest of Somalia,
والعنف المتفشي في سائر أجزاء الصومال،
where peacebuilding has been mostly top-down.
حيث كان بناء السلام ذات اتجاه تنازلي تقريبًا.
And there are several other cases
وتوجد حالات أخرى عديدة
in which local, grassroots conflict resolution
حيث صنع حل النزاع الشعبي المحلي
has made a crucial difference.
فرقًا حاسمًا.
So if we want international peacebuilding to work,
لذا إذا أردنا النجاح لجهود بناء السلام الدولية،
in addition to any top-down intervention,
وأيضًا لأي تدخل تنازلي،
conflicts must be resolved from the bottom up.
فينبغي أن تُحل النزاعات من الأسفل إلى الأعلى.
And again, it's not that national and international tensions don't matter.
ومجددًا، هذا لا يعني أن التوترات القومية والدولية غير مهمة.
They do.
بل هي مهمة.
And it's not that national and international peacebuilding
وهذا لا يعني أن جهود بناء السلام القومية والدولية
isn't necessary.
غير ضرورية.
It is.
بل هي ضرورية.
Instead, it is that both macro-level and micro-level peacebuilding are needed
إنما بناء السلام الجزئي والكلي كلاهما لازمان
to make peace sustainable,
لجعل السلام مستدام.
and local nongovernmental organizations,
وعلى المنظمات المحلية غير الحكومية
local authorities and civil society representatives
والسلطات المحلية وممثلي المجتمع المدني
should be the main actors in the bottom-up process.
أن يكونوا هم الممثلون الأساسيون في العملية التصاعدية.
So of course, there are obstacles.
وبالطبع، توجد عوائق.
Local actors often lack the funding
حيث يفتقر الممثلون المحليون للدعم المالي
and sometimes the logistical means and the technical capacity
وأحيانًا للوسائل اللوجستية والإمكانات الفنية
to implement effective, local peacebuilding programs.
اللازمة لتنفيذ برامج بناء سلام محلية فعالة.
So international actors should expand their funding and support
لذا ينبغي على الممثلين الدوليين توسيع تمويلهم ودعمهم
for local conflict resolution.
المخصص لحل النزاعات المحلية.
As for Congo, what can be done?
بالنسبة للكونغو، ما الذي يمكن فعله؟
After two decades of conflict and the deaths of millions,
بعد عقدين من النزاع وخسارة ملايين الأرواح،
it's clear that we need to change our approach.
يتضح لنا أننا نحتاج إلى تغيير منهجنا في التعامل مع الحالة.
Based on my field research,
ووفقًا لبحثي الميداني،
I believe that international and Congolese actors
أعتقد أن على الممثلين الدوليين والكونغوليين
and the promotion of inter-community reconciliation.
فعلى سبيل المثال، في مقاطعة كيفوس
So for instance, in the province of the Kivus,
معهد Life and Peace وشركاؤه الكونغوليون
the Life and Peace Institute and its Congolese partners
أقاموا منتديات بين أفراد المجتمع
have set up inter-community forums
لمناقشة تفاصيل النزاعات المحلية حول البلاد
to discuss the specifics of local conflicts over land,
وقد ساهمت تلك المنتديات في إيجاد حلول للسيطرة على العنف.
and these forums have found solutions to help manage the violence.
وهذا هو نوع البرامج اللازمة بشدة
That's the kind of program that is sorely needed
عبر الكونغو الشرقية.
throughout eastern Congo.
من خلال برامج كهذه
It's with programs like this
سنتمكن من مساعدة أُناس مثل إيزابيل وزوجها
that we can help people like Isabelle and her husband.
إنها ليست عصا سحرية
So these will not be magic wands,
ولكن لأنها تأخذ في الاعتبار الأسباب الجذرية للعنف
but because they take into account deeply rooted causes of the violence,
استطاعت أن تكون نقطة تحول
they could definitely be game-changers.
شكرًا لكم
Thank you.
(تصفيق)